right. Let's talk about how Salesforce has weathered this
pandemic in this economic crisis. Um, everyone went
through an accelerated digital transformation, and I assume even
a digital company like Salesforce had to do it.
How long did it tell you? Take you to
get on your feet to get your bearings? Yeah
, that's absolutely right. I mean, it's It's
almost embarrassing when you're a technology company and you encounter
your like this because it shows all the cracks in
the foundation, right? All the all the ways
you depended on your office space and all the all
the parts of your business that weren't digital. You
know, the term that I use for the for
that feeling in marches, paralysis, you know,
we just you know, as you know, we're
in event oriented company. We have 200,000 people descend
on San Francisco for Dream Force. Every year we're
on airplanes in our customers offices, and I think
it was the that sense of unfamiliarity that really lead
Thio. I think a paralysis particularly for our customer
facing teams, you know, that are used to
being, you know, face to face with our
customers on board, you know, I don't know
if it was a month or a few weeks.
It felt like forever. At the time, I
could tell you that. Andi, I think that
we we really had to be intentional about transforming our
culture in the face of what we've been calling this
all digital work anywhere world that we're in right now
. Andi, when I say intentional kind of goes
back to our roots, we do in all hands
with all 54,000 employees every week. And we have
since the beginning, the pandemic. We literally have
not done that since Mark and Parker started this place
21 years ago, you know, But we have
54,000 people on the zoom call. You know,
it's crazy and we're really focused on, you know
, how do you work today? We have this
small we call participation, which means just get on
the phone, ask your customer how they can help
. How can you help them right now? It's
about relevance, you know, it's saying, Hey
, all these technologies we've had for a long time
, but what's a relevant conversation today is pretty different
than it. Waas. Ah, few weeks ago
, a few months ago. And it's about enablement
, you know, which is really saying, How
could we train every single employee in the new way
that they have to work on? Do we really
adopted those principles? Participation, relevance, enablement And
again, this kind of operating cadence that is very
intentional, very active kind of a culture of action
is way I describe it, and I think it's
really helped us get through the initial stages, the
pandemic. And now I feel like we're really firing
on all cylinders. What was the most surprising barrier
that you encountered in this process? You know,
I think, um, mhm the every single department
, every single function had to change at the same
time. And so, you know, you really
realized where people were sort of dependent on the machinery
of a large company. You know, whether it
was your sales executive and you're dependent on showing up
to these events to engage with your customers, and
all of a sudden that's gone and you need to
have you know, you need to be personally proactive
to do it. You're a marketer, depending on
the standard ways that you generate leads on all of
a sudden. All of those channels are not available
to you, and the one channel left, which
is digital, is completely saturated because every company in
the world went there overnight. And what I would
say is that really demands a beginner's mind and it
creativity that I don't think every individual at every company
really has. And and I think it's fascinating.
Yeah, so it's a principle. I think Marc
Benioff really embraces that I love. I love that
principle, you know, and sort of an expert
mind, you know, on Lee knows one possibility
for an a beginner's mind. Everything's a possibility.
And I think in the age of you know,
covid-ninteen, it's really multiple crises at the same time
a health crisis, an economic crisis, a social
justice crisis, a leadership crisis in this country.
You know, you need to show up and say
, Okay, I need to re imagine how how
we do business on bond. That's what I really
think it was. A big in his mind is
you know, we know what really differentiates us as
a company. Our customers know what differentiates us,
and we're enabling a digital transformation where we're exactly what
our customers need in this moment. But how we
engage with our customers needed to completely transform. And
if you'd asked me last year could you run the
business from home with no events, I would have
laughed at you. Not only did we do that
, we did it with no preparation, you know
, and that's what's really remarkable right now for us
and for all of our customers. I think it's
proof that this new digital way of working is possible
, and I think what's exciting about that when the
spirit of this beginner's mind does, it really begs
the question. How are we gonna work on the
other side of this? You know, when it's
not imposed on us and we got stuck in our
home office is because we have to be, You
know, now that we've proven as a society that
hey, I can order groceries online and you know
meetings don't necessarily need to be in person when that
all becomes optional. What is the transform version of
ourselves on the other side? And that's what I'm
really excited about across our customer base actually is really
seeing the leaders who are treating this as an opportunity
to transform rather than just a crisis to respond.
Thio. So what do you see on the other
side of this for? For Salesforce in particular?
I mean, how how is it going to change
the way you operate, the way you get your
work done? It's a great question. It is
the most challenging question to answer. I laughed,
predicting the future of this year feels sort of comically
hard, because I wouldn't have been right at any
point. You know, it's every every time I
think I've figured out this year. Some new crazy
thing happens. But with that caveat, you know
, right now, I would say it has proven
that this all digital work anywhere world can work like
we can work in this environment. So it does
beg the question about what is the role of the
office? What is the role of a headquarters on
Bond? I'll start with a few sort of sober
realities. One is, I think this year is
not sustainable for a lot of our employees. We
measure this, and on average, our employees have
1.7 more hours of meetings on their calendar every day
. Uh, this pandemic than before. In June
, we surveyed our customers, and only 23% of
people want to return to the office. We today
that 72% people are clamoring for, you know,
some semblance of normalcy. Other hand, I think
, you know, I was talking to Matt Mullen
because the CEO of WordPress, which is one of
the largest content management systems in the world, but
notably it's a company that's been distributed from day one
s. I laugh all of a sudden he is
the expert on what we're all experiencing, and he
made a really good point to me. What you
said. We're not really experiencing distributed work in the
way that I thought of when I created WordPress.
We're experience of pandemic i e. It's been imposed
upon us as opposed to an intentional design of our
culture. And so what I would say is on
the other side of this, now that we've really
learned that we can operate in this distributed way,
I think it's going to really change the way we
think about our physical spaces, you know, maybe
more purpose driven. Maybe people don't We have assigned
desks. Maybe it's more neighborhood seating. Maybe instead
of saying, you know, we're gonna work away
from the office on Fridays were to say, Hey
, everyone's gonna work in the office on Thursday so
that we really are focused on teaming rather than treating
remote work is an individual decision. E think all
of these things will, I think, for the
companies that really are intentional about building their cultures.
Um, I think it's really amazing opportunity because one
of the things that I think it does mean is
you can recruit from, or geography ease. It
can get you know, your employees working parents just
a ton more flexibility if we do it right,
s. So I'm kind of looking forward to the
day where you don't have the stress of it feeling
imposed on you. And you could really say,
How do we treat the lessons of 2020 as an
asset that we can use to transform our culture going
forward? That is definitely a lot of us are
thinking about that. And it will be fascinating when
the context isn't as frightening as it is now to
think about it with a clearer head. Um,
you know, you said that you mentioned the culture
a couple of times. Salesforce has 50,000 plus employees
. How how do you shift your culture when you're
50,000 plus employees in what must be dozens and dozens
of markets, all all of your employees working from
home? How do you How do you align and
how do you ship your culture? It is a
really interesting question, and, um well, first
, I'll say that we've been really intentional about building
our culture. I think every great company is and
should be on DWI really take great pride that our
culture isn't just, um, looking inwards at our
employees. It's really something that we express to our
customers into our partners into our communities. And it's
why, from day one, every salesforce tower across
the globe, we have many of them. In
many major cities, we have the top floor is
called the Ohana floor, and it's a floor that
is actually available not just us but to our partners
into the community, to use for, for example
, for charity fundraisers. It's the reason why you
go to ah Salesforce event like one of our world
tours or dream force. It looks like our offices
and our offices look like our events, you know
? And it's, uh, we really try to
say that our culture is something that we want to
be, not a poster on the cafeteria wall,
and that's something superficial, like our culture is something
that is part of our events. It's a part
of the way we express ourselves to our community.
Um, and it's interesting when I gave all those
examples those events, the office space is a lot
of those have gone away. And so it really
begs the question in this, you know, distributed
, all digital world were in. How do you
imbue culture? How do you onboard new employees to
our culture? I think we've done a good job
. As I said, just by being intentional,
you know, we've spent a lot of time really
focusing on, you know, culture not being again
from the superficial values on the on the coffee next
to the coffee machine. This is something I think
all of our employees can really articulate. You also
wonder how much are we borrowing from culture that we've
built pre pandemic. You know, if this continued
on for five more years, would your culture start
toe have cracks in the foundation, and I can't
say that I have. You know, I think
that's part of it. I really dio you know
. And so I really think when I think about
culture going forward, I think one of the things
I would say is it's really inclusive concept. You
know, culture is something that you need to really
authentically live, because culture is not something in posting
the top culture is something that you experience when you
interact with your colleagues and that your customers experience when
they interact with you on DSO. I do believe
that we maintain that, you know, really inclusive
view of culture or something we can maintain even in
this in this new way of working, I wonder
if you'd be willing to share with our audience.
Um, some of the mistakes you may have made
along the way. You know, if we ever
face another crisis again of the breath of the one
we're facing now, what will you know not to
dio It is a great question and it's something I've
actually talked to a lot of our customers about as
well What high level pattern I will give you some
examples is where we didn't change fast enough. You
know, I think that in the beginning of this
pandemic, every CEO I talked Thio would talk about
the crisis is something that they would weather, you
know, something that they would get through so that
on the other side they could go back to business
as usual. All of the customers in our customer
base and all areas where we've done better to or
where we lean into the change. There was a
wonderful quote from the chief digital officer of Loreal who
said something along lines of we accomplished in three months
. What would have taken us three years to Dio
? And I think that that there's, you know
, that old colloquialism like Don't let a good crisis
go to waste. I think that's right mentality in
these, which is, you know, um and
Thio answer your question more directly at the beginning.
In our particular customer facing parts of our company,
we treated as something toe wait out and we didn't
lean into Okay, how do we show up for
our customers digitally in a way that's actually compatible this
pandemic? And you know that means that, you
know, we're challenging our teams to say if you're
not on zoom every day with your customers, what
are you doing? You know what? We should
be here to help them in their time of greatest
need. Um, and I think that we didn't
do that right away. We were too cautious,
Andi And I think if we I Your question almost
gives me PTSD because I don't want to experience another
year like this. But if we ever encounter something
like this, I think we're gonna really lean into
the changes implied by the crisis rather than treating the
crisis. Is something temporary, Andi, even if
it is temporary, it just might. We use
is on transform our business. And based on you
know what, you still when we began this conversation
, you said you were in events oriented company and
that, you know, dream Force. If anyone
has ever been in San Francisco for dream force,
it's in San Francisco, right? It iss Yeah
, yeah, it's crazy event. How are you
going to think about events in the future? Yeah
. You know, I think it's going to end
up in and not in, or you know,
I think I'm looking for the welcoming 200,000 people to
San Francisco next year. Knock on wood. Uh
, if this vaccine does what we all hope it
will dio. But what we've really learned is how
to do digital events like the one we're doing right
now. Incredibly valuable, right? You can watch
it in a time shifted way. You can watch
it on your own schedule. Um, the two
of us didn't need to travel to have this conversation
right now, and it probably lowered some of the
barriers to us having this conversation. So I think
when I think about it, and actually I've had
this experience. I've heard this from many executives.
I have conversations with so many CEOs every week,
and I wonder if I would have had that same
level of conversation if we felt like we had to
be in person to have them. So, in
general, what I hope on the other side of
this, for our events and our culture broadly is
embracing what we've learned and making it not snap back
to the way it was, but really augment the
way we run the company. But this has been
so interesting. I wish we could talk for a
now, er, but But unfortunately, unfortunately,
we can't. So I want to thank you.
And I want to thank everyone in our audience for